<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd in the Cathedral of Lincoln, July XVIII, 1681 being the Assize-Monday / by Daniel Nicols ...</title>
            <author>Nicols, Daniel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52332</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1142</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36617</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15745890</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15745890</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104596</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52332)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104596)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1153:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd in the Cathedral of Lincoln, July XVIII, 1681 being the Assize-Monday / by Daniel Nicols ...</title>
                  <author>Nicols, Daniel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.G. and J.P. for Joseph Lawson ... and sold by Richard Chiswell ... and Thomas Sawbridge ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: An assize-sermon.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 1st, XII, 14-15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104596:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd in the <hi>CATHEDRAL</hi> of <hi>LINCOLN, July XVIII.</hi> 1681. Being the ASSIZE-MONDAY.</p>
            <p>By <hi>DANIEL NICOLS,</hi> A. M. Rector of <hi>Scotton</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire:</hi> and ſometimes Fellow of St. <hi>John</hi>'s in <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. G.</hi> and <hi>J. P.</hi> for <hi>Joſeph Lawſon,</hi> Bookſeller at the <hi>Bail</hi> of <hi>Lincoln;</hi> and Sold by <hi>Richard Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard; and <hi>Thomas Sawbridge,</hi> at the <hi>Three Flower-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luces</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:104596:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104596:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful Sir <hi>CHRISTOPHER NEVILE,</hi> K<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> High-Sheriff of the County of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is very great pity, that thoſe who pretend to Religion, ſhould be given to Faction, as if Religion (I mean true) which is but one) could Patronize Diviſion; as groſs a miſtake as Pope <hi>Adrian</hi>'s Interpretation was of St. <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s Liturgy, which was preferred to that of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> becauſe it was torn into a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand bits and ſcraps; whereas the other remained whole, and therefore by him judg'd unfit to be uſed. Who could believe that a Pope ſhould be guilty of ſuch a conſtruction! Sure I am, he hath given the ſame meaſures to many of his Sons and Daughters, who (though they pretend Liberty of Conſcience) yet are very angry that their own ſmall conceits about Religion (which are divers, and contrary each to other) cannot be counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced
<pb facs="tcp:104596:3"/>
by Law; and will rather chuſe to have a thouſand Religious lyes impoſed, (ſince they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have their wills) than that Religion to flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, which is at preſent Eſtabliſhed. But as God is one, and his Name one; ſo is it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, that the ſolemn Worſhip, which all pay to him, in their publick addreſſes, ſhould be but one, that with one heart and lip his praiſe may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted by all: This was the ancient and primitive Sacrifice which the Church did acceptably offer up, <hi>Acts 2.46, 47. And they continuing daily with one accord in the Temple, and breaking bread from houſe to houſe, did eat their meat with gladneſs and ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart, praiſing God,</hi> &amp;c. And you will eaſily perceive, Sir, that Religion in the Fountain (where the water is living and pure) differs far from what ſhe is called at the foot of the hill, after her ſtreams have paſſed through the corrupt brains of a confuſed multitude. It's a melancholly, doleful ſight, to obſerve a vaſt number of phrantick perſons, pretending to the height of skill in Religious Chymiſtry, as if their inſpired noddles were the only limbecks to extract the ſpirit and quinteſſence of Religion;
<pb facs="tcp:104596:3"/>
as if they only knew the ſecrets of the Kingdom, and have been taken up into the third Heaven, raviſhed with joys unſpeakable, fed with hidden <hi>Manna.</hi> Some of theſe are to be pitied; ſuch (I mean) as are humble, willing to be informed, who have been cheated out of their good deſigns, by the ſubtilty of wicked men: the reſt deſerve the laſh, and ought to be ſcourged into better manners. The great deſign of theſe Religious Quacks, is to ſet men at an infinite diſtance from the ſolemn ſervice of Almighty God: and the firſt leſſon they teach their Children and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes, is, that our Liturgy is Popery, that our Miniſters are Antichriſtian, that we have all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the mark of the Beaſt. Some of their Novices I have met with, who inſtead of diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, have turn'd over their Bibles, always turned down at certain places; amongſt the reſt, to be ſure the <hi>13 Revelat. 16, 17.</hi> muſt be one: <hi>Would to God they were cut off, that hunt after ſouls to deſtroy them; that creep into houſes, to lead captive ſilly women.</hi> No ſeverity can be too great for thoſe who exerciſe cruelty and tyranny over them, for whom Chriſt has ſhed his moſt precious blood. I confeſs, Sir,
<pb facs="tcp:104596:4"/>
that an Addreſs of this nature can no way be ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to a Dedication; nor had either it, or the enſuing diſcourſe ever ſeen the light, if the deſire of the Right Honourable the Judges, with the ſelect and choice company of Knights and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Grand-Jury, had not been as forcible as a Command, which I cannot but mention as an excuſe to my appearance in Print; For how could I deny ſo general an expectation, without Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of diſreſpect?</p>
            <p>To your ſelf, Sir, give me leave to plead the deſign of this Preface, to be a Chaos to that which followeth, hoping that ſome of thoſe perſons, who have taken up their Religion upon truſt, will be perſwaded to reflect upon themſelves, and judge how inconſiſtent it is with true Piety, to abſent themſelves from the publick Worſhip of God, and be reckoned amongſt thoſe who break the peace, ſpoil the beauty, diſcourage the friends, incourage the enemies of our Church. That the God of Heaven would ſucceed the good deſign of this Paper to his own glory, the comfort and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of our much-deſpiſed and neglected Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; That he would pour out of his bleſsings,
<pb facs="tcp:104596:4"/>
both Temporal and Spiritual, upon you, and your truly religious and devout Lady, ſhall be the daily prayer of him, who is glad of an opportunity to declare to the World, that he is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very much obliged, moſt thankful, and moſt humble Servant, <hi>DANIEL NICOLS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:104596:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104596:5"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 SAM. 12.14, 15.</bibl>
                  <p>If ye will fear the Lord, and ſerve him, and obey his voice, and not rebel againſt the Commandment of the Lord, then ſhall both ye, and the King, that reigneth over you, continue following the Lord your God. But if ye will not obey the Voice of the Lord, but rebel againſt the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord, then ſhall the hand of the Lord be againſt you, as it was againſt your Fathers.</p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>SATAN was always an Enemy to Religion, not only true, but falſe, and would (if it were poſſible) force all pretences to it out of the World; for whereſoever that is profeſſed, a Deity muſt be acknowledged; and how is it credible, that he who affects Supremacy himſelf, ſhould indure a Superior Power, if he could help it? But becauſe the Character of a God is engraven upon the tables of our hearts, therefore does he improve his utmoſt Policy and Power, to ſpoil the beauty, and exact proportion of true Religion, repreſenting it to ſome as harſh and ſevere, that none may dare to take up the profeſſion of it, but the Sons of <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> men compoſed of ſlaviſh, dreggy, and melancholly hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors: To others he renders it ſo facile and eaſie, that it's impoſſible for them to keep their Religion and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104596:6"/>
to their luſts. Many he benighteth with thick Egyptian-darkneſs, perſwading, either that there are more Gods than one, or no God at all, or (that which is as bad as the worſt) that he himſelf muſt have divine Worſhip and Honour. But he that loves the Souls of his creatures, hath always declared to the world, by the moſt curious and exact Government of the ſame, that he is a holy, juſt, and righteous God, and expecteth of them that Worſhip him, that they be holy and virtuous in all manner of Converſation, and eſpecially to his peculiar people he hath given ſevere and ſtrict Commands, to obſerve the pattern given them from the Mount, and not to ſwerve a hairs breadth from the ſame, appearing more jealous in the inſtance of divine Worſhip and Honour, than in any other concern. This is one great reaſon (if not the only) of the charge given in the Text; <hi>If ye will fear the Lord, and ſerve him, and obey his voice,</hi> &amp;c. For the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were now innovating in State-affairs, chopping and changing of Governments, Kings are deſired in the place of Judges; and that which gave the greateſt occaſion of diſpleaſure to the great King of Heaven, was not (as I humbly conceive) either the change of Government conſidered in it ſelf, or the deſire of that change, but rather the copy and example, which they chuſe to follow in this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> and the Nations round about them, which were all of them Idolatrous, and curſed of God; thoſe muſt perſwade them that it is better to have a King, than a Judge (although of God's immediate choice) to rule over them. Now as all changes and innovations are dangerous, ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104596:6"/>
here in Special, for this reaſon, leſt Conformity to them in Civils, might by degrees incline them to a Conformity in Spirituals alſo; for it is commonly ſeen, that the Diſcipline and Government of the Church, does follow that of the State; and it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, that if there be not ſome harmony and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent between the one and the other, there muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily enſue Convulſions both of Church and State. And it is no ways improbable, that <hi>Heathens</hi> (though fond and fooliſh enough in their conceits about Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) did, to avoid theſe ruptures and ſtorms, adviſe their Diſciples, not rigorouſly, in ſtrange Countreys, to adhere to the Rites and Ceremonies of their own Gods, but rather to condeſcend, for the ſake of Peace, to Worſhip the Gods of the place, according to their own cuſtoms. This compliance (though it might paſs well enough, in point of Policy, in thoſe places, where no true God was worſhipped) yet cannot here be endured; to prevent which, the holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had frequently inculcated this Command, <hi>Not to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſtrange Gods, nor to walk in their ways;</hi> which were called <hi>Via Amorrheorum,</hi> to keep themſelves cloſe to the pattern of the Mount; and as ſome conceive thoſe Prohibitions mentioned <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.19. <hi>Thou ſhalt not let thy cattel gender with divers kinds: thou ſhalt not ſow thy fields with divers kinds, and a garment of divers kinds of Linſey-woolſey ſhall not come upon thee,</hi> are purpoſely deſign'd by Almighty God to keep the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> at the vaſteſt diſtance from ſome Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, and Idolatrous cuſtoms, then in force with the Heathens near them.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:104596:7"/>
            <p>This muſt however be the cauſe of thoſe multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied phraſes, and flood of words poured out in the text, and other places of the ſame nature, ſo much ſignifying one and the ſame thing; that if we had not a reverence for Divine Writ, and a through belief, that it proceedeth from the God of Truth, the imputation of Battology, ſo common amongſt Heathens, or Tautology, ſo common amongſt our ſelves, would not ſeem injurious.</p>
            <p>The words then under a double Hypotheſis, contain a ſtrict and ſevere charge to the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to keep cloſe to that form of Religious Worſhip, which the King of kings had Eſtabliſhed amongſt them: For though he had now, upon their importunity, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulged them in Politicks, giving them leave to be like other Nations in Kingly Government; yet he expected that he himſelf, as God, ſhould be worſhipped accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own Preſcriptions.</p>
            <p>To the firſt Hypotheſis, for their incouragement, is annexed a Promiſe, <hi>If ye will fear,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then both ye, and the King which reigneth over you, ſhall continue fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Lord.</hi> To the latter Hypotheſis, is added a Threatning, to check Diſobedience; <hi>If ye will not obey the voice of the Lord, then ſhall the hand of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Hypothetical Propoſitions may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced <hi>Categorically,</hi> after this manner: That a zealous Obſervation of true Religion, is the moſt infallible way of ſecuring Peace between the Trinity of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, mentioned in the Text, <hi>God, the King, and the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104596:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The neglect, or contempt of Religion, does moſt effectually break Peace between God and a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and conſequently bring ruine and deſtruction upon the ſame.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe (if duly handled) will involve the latter, where three things muſt be inquired after.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What that Religion is of the Text. Then how it comes by its cementing and uniting Nature. Laſtly, What the Priviledge or Promiſe ſignifieth, which is annexed, <hi>Then ſhall both ye and the King,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, what is Religion? If there were but one or two in the world, it might be no hard matter to define them: but when every Town and Village almoſt is full of Faction, and every Faction hath a different perſwaſion; and this opinion, or perſwaſion, muſt be cryed up for Religion, Who is able to coin Diffinitions faſt enough? And methinks it ſhould not a little conduce to confirm thoſe in their preſent Faith, who yet retain ſoundneſs in their Judgments, to take a ſhort view of the phantaſtical dreams of men about Religion. One tells you, that the very Genius of it is Separation, and pleads Scripture for it: <hi>Come out from amongſt them, leſt ye partake of her plagues;</hi> and dar'ſt, with the proud <hi>Donaſtiſt,</hi> exclude Heaven, and confine to Hell, all ſuch as jump not with them in all their blaſphemies. A ſecond defines his <hi>per Illuminationem, &amp; Revelationem,</hi> and, with the ſtately <hi>Greek,</hi> ſuppoſeth none to ſee but himſelf; all the world, at moſt, have but one eye, whilſt he ſees per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly with both.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:104596:8"/>
            <p>If you will compare Old and New <hi>Rome</hi> together, you will find them to accord very well in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Religion: <hi>Cicero</hi> thus deſcribeth it, <hi>Religio eſt quae curam affert caeremoniis divini cultas:</hi> And who knows not, that the Religion of <hi>Rome</hi> at preſent, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts rather in waſhing the out-ſides of diſhes and platters, in croſſing, and cringing, and creeping, than in the Devotion and Worſhip of the Soul; which cannot be very intent, whilſt buſied in an exact ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of ſo many External Rites. The truth is, the multitude of Ceremonies impoſed by that Church, hath devoured the greateſt part of her ſubſtantial, Religious Worſhip; but becauſe, without Religion, ſhe cannot pretend to be the Church of God, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt her Ceremonies ſtand for her Religion. The <hi>Atheiſt</hi> defines Religion by fear, and tells you, That
<q>Primus in Orbe Deos fecit Timor.</q>
And will force himſelf, like <hi>Lucian,</hi> to laugh and ſcoff at Religion, as if it were nothing but the pretty device of Politicians, to keep fools in awe: Thoſe are ſome of the dreams, and mad conceits of men, about Religion, which I produce meerly as a taſte of thoſe infinite conceptions, whereby Satan works cunningly upon the minds of men, perſwading them, either that Religion is not yet defined, and ſo leaves them in the Labyrinths of Sceptiſm; or elſe that there is no God, nor Religion at all, and ſo drowns them in Irreligion and Atheiſm. Thus this beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Virgin is every minute in danger to be deſtroyed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104596:8"/>
by the beaſts of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> the latter ſort; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>floured by the former, tho pretended Lovers; who, by their abominable Separations, have torn into pieces the ſeamleſs garment which Chriſt had beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified her with; and have put upon her a Coat of divers colours and patches, repreſenting rather the ſpots and changes of the Moon, than the luſtre and beauty of the Sun; ſhe is become a <hi>ſtone of ſtumbling, a rock of offence,</hi> ſcarcely known; ſo miſerably diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured, that ſhe is like that Stone which <hi>Pliny</hi> calls <hi>Achates, tot variis inumbratus coloribus, ut unum lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem eſſe, minimè credamus.</hi> But thanks be to God, that in this night of confuſion, ſome of us know what we Worſhip, and what our Worſhip is; and to ſatisfie men of unbiaſſed principles, I need go no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the Text to fetch a true Deſcription of both; for it muſt neceſſarily follow, from the nature of the promiſe and threatning, that the Worſhip we offer is to the living God, who made Heaven and Earth, according to the Precepts of his revealed Will. This is our ſolemn and publick Sacrifice, ſo defined by St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> in his <hi>Civitas Dei:</hi> and thus it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from the private Devotions of a Religious Soul; which tho it be very acceptable to the great God, yet falls far ſhort of that acceptance, which the union of hearts and voices in publick Aſſemblies findeth with him: He hath always loved the gates of <hi>Zion,</hi> better than the dwelling-places of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> the reaſon of which, the holy Prophet giveth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.4. Becauſe <hi>thither went up the Tribes, the Tribes of the Lord, unto the Teſtimony of Iſrael, to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104596:9"/>
give thanks unto the Name of the Lord.</hi> When a multitude ſpeak the ſame thing, and conſpire toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to offer up their Sacrifices to the Lord, then does the Glory of the Lord appear; then does he manifeſt his gracious Preſence, as he did his Glory in the days of <hi>Solomon,</hi> 2 Chron. 5.13, 14. <hi>It came to paſs when the Trumpets and Singers were as one, to make one ſound to be heard in praiſing and thanking the Lord: and when they lift up their voice with the Cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals, and Trumpets, and Inſtruments of Muſick, and praiſed the Lord, ſaying, For he is good, for his mercy endureth for ever: that then the houſe was filled with a cloud, even the houſe of the Lord; ſo that the Prieſts could not ſtand to miniſter, by reaſon of the Cloud: for the glory of the Lord had filled the houſe of God.</hi> The want of this ſweet harmony, and conſent of Souls in the Worſhip of God, is the reaſon why our Church mourns at this day; her viſible Members ſpeak not the ſame things, but divers, and contrary one to another. <hi>Babel</hi> is found in <hi>Bethel;</hi> confuſion in the houſe of God, as if we would force that to be the true and genuine meaning of our Saviour, when he brought the Everlaſting Goſpel into the World; <hi>I come not to ſend Peace, but a Sword.</hi> How unlike are we to thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, who came up thither to Worſhip; and tho of divers Nations and Languages, yet w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e they of the ſame Religion, from whence undoubtedly they were called <hi>Jews?</hi> We, tho we uſe no other but our Mother-tongue in the Service of God, yet have we more Religions, than they were Nations. Can any good come out
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104596:9"/>
of this <hi>Galilee?</hi> Is it likely that a fire ſhould be quenched with Oyl, or a healing plaiſter be made of Corroſives? Let us fear, rather leſt a Church divided againſt it ſelf ſhould not ſtand: <hi>Rome</hi> rides faſter, and gets more ground upon the ſpeck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led horſe of our own diviſions, than upon the prancing Genet of her own worſhip; ſhe cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly does her work, and ſits ſtill, whilſt we, by our Separations, are perfecting her deſigns in our own ruines; and leſt any ſhould wonder why ſo magiſterially I ſeem to obtrude my own Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the World, let him but impartially conſider how the old Axiom is again revived in <hi>Rome [divide &amp; impera];</hi> and then let him tell me whether the reaſon of our preſent impotency and weakneſs, and of their hopes and expectations, does not proceed principally from thoſe curſed and ſinful Diviſions amongſt Proteſtants?</p>
            <p>My humble Addreſs therefore to this Right Honourable and Noble Aſſembly, is, That in your reſpective places, as Judges, as Magiſtrates, as Nobles, as Gentlemen, you would glorifie your God, ſave (if poſſible) your Country from that deſtruction, which as a dark Cloud hangs over her head, that you would imbelliſh and perfume your names to all generations, by honouring Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, by vindicating her innocent beauty from the vile aſſaults, and bruitiſh rapes of prophane and diſſolute men. Aſſert the ſolemnity of our Worſhip, by your publick, conſtant, and reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial attendance, againſt all Detractors, who ſet up
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104596:10"/>
Altar againſt Altar, Church againſt Church, and make it the greateſt part of their Religion, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame ours. Defend the purity and ſimplicity of it, from the ſuperſtitious and corrupt mixtures of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by a generous and rational obſervance of decency and order in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God. Religion takes no pleaſure, either in a naſty, ſlovenly behaviour, or delight in a Phariſaical gaudery. Our Ceremonies are few in number, eaſily told, as eaſily underſtood, not like thoſe of the other Church, a load in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable, ſcarcely inferior to the Bondage of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> State. Again, Let me beſeech you to ſhow your Zeal for it in the Preſence of <hi>Atheiſts;</hi> Let not Hell (tho it be broken looſe in our days) make you aſhamed of your Crucified Saviour, and his Royal Laws. It argueth a poor, ſneaking, ingentile ſpirit, when men ſhall be he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctored out of their Religion, by a company of Sots, that have no God but their Belly, and underſtand no other pleaſure, but what Bruits do find. <hi>Hand ulla Numina expaveſcunt Coelitum, Ventri offerent Deos ignorant caeteros,</hi> as <hi>Euripides</hi> expreſſeth them. Theſe are the <hi>Antichriſts</hi> which endeavour pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly and privately the ruine of our Religion, a Jewel too precious to be loſt, if you pleaſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſecond particular, the healing and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting nature of it: It's the Balſome of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Pandora of all excellent Virtues, which undoubtedly will heal all wounds in Church and State, may they be applied. But that which does
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104596:10"/>
not a little advance the Excellency of it is, that the perfection which ſhe challengeth as her own, does not proceed meerly from the abſtracted bleſſing of the great God, but in part from the curious compoſure of that Spirit which God has endued her with, which her very Name, as (St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> and <hi>Propertius</hi> teſtifie) does ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, this being that which faſteneth the Soul and Conſcience to God and Goodneſs. The <hi>Greeks</hi> tranſlate it by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and thoſe that joyned themſelves as Proſelytes to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, were called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſometimes waiters for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, longing for the Revelation of the Meſſias. We may judge of the force that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion has, by the combining nature of Superſtition and Will-worſhip, which (as <hi>Lactantius</hi> obſerves) is but <hi>verae Religionis unitatrix,</hi> it makes men all of one mind and judgment; <hi>Pignoratos reddit ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> it cauſeth them to pawn their Souls, and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and Eſtates alſo, one to another. <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> though deſperate enemies before, were then made friends, when Chriſt was to be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Old <hi>Rome</hi> will dye to the laſt man <hi>pro aris, &amp; focis;</hi> new <hi>Rome</hi> is, at this day, as zealous for her new-coined Devotions, and will unite all the World over againſt thoſe, whom they are pleaſed to Damn for <hi>Hereticks:</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> ſtand as ſtifly to the Traditions of their Forefathers, the <hi>Rabbins</hi> and Doctors of their Church, as the <hi>Turks</hi> to the Precepts of their Alcoran, or we to the Old and New Teſtaments. Now, if the name of Religion,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104596:11"/>
though it be falſe, carrieth with it ſuch Magical force and power, to how much more may true Religion pretend? He that reads the Hiſtory of the Ten Perſecutions, when the native and ſimple beauty of Religion raviſhed the Souls of thoſe bleſſed Martyrs, will eaſily believe that ſhe is ſtrong and mighty, as well as amiable and lovely. The pacifick argument which <hi>Abraham</hi> urgeth to <hi>Lot,</hi> when there was diſcord between their herds-men, was this, That they were of the ſame Religion, Gen. 13.8. <hi>Let there be no ſtrife, I pray thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween me and thee, between my herds men and thy herds-men, for we be brethren: Hoc eſt, Fide, &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligione;</hi> and the more cogent was his requeſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Canaanite</hi> and the <hi>Perizite,</hi> men that were ſtrangers to God and Religion, dwelt then in the Land. No ſooner had the influence of it touch'd the Souls of the Three thouſand, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.44, but they were together, and had all things common. I confeſs, when Religion began to grow into Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, then ſprang up Diviſions; a parting of Minds and Souls, as well as of Purſes and Eſtates; then was the Common of Chriſtianity turn'd into incloſures, when one cries out, <hi>I am of Paul, another, I am of Apollos; a third, I am for Caephas; and a fourth, I am for Chriſt;</hi> that is neither for Miniſters, nor Ordinances, but only for Jeſus and his Spirit: But who dar'ſt impute this to Religion, when St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells you it proceeds from the fleſh, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.4. <hi>For while one ſaith, I am of Paul, and another, I am of Apollo, are ye not carnal?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:104596:11"/>
            <p>But the glory of true Religion will be more apparent; If you obſerve, (1.) That ſhe is a moſt perfect piece of Beauty, and therefore of her own nature attractive; for love to its proper ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, is ſtrong, and never at reſt, till it does <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in amatum;</hi> the drawing out of thoſe lines of Perfection upon her, was not truſted to the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Apelles,</hi> or the curious finger of any Mortal, but the unerring hand of God himſelf; nor was there any Copy or Exemplar to draw by, but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Original of her Perfection; in her ſhineth forth his Wiſdom, Goodneſs, Mercy, Patience, Juſtice, Purity, and all other commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable Virtues to the Sons of <hi>Adam:</hi> All other Beauties, in reſpect of this, are but <hi>tenebrae.</hi> What you ſee in the vaulted Heavens (which made the holy Prophet admire), the beauty of Sun, Moon, and Stars; what you ſee upon Earth in the Spring, when nature has put on her rich embroidery; whatever can be ſaid of, or for Riches, Honours, Pleaſures, Preferments in the World, are nothing in compariſon of her love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. If that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. the exact and comely diſpoſition of the Worſhip of God could be found in our Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, where all perſons with one conſent ſhould offer up their Spiritual Sacrifices to Almighty God, Angels would rejoyce, and delight to joyn with us, and make up the Chorus of ſweet-fingers in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Papiſts would no longer have occaſion to ſay, that we are <hi>Fracti corde, &amp; ore.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:104596:12"/>
The ſober part of Diſſenters, that have truely tender Conſciences, would no longer keep at a diſtance; you would then ſee the Antepaſt of Eternity, when Religion ſhall aſcend the <hi>Meridian</hi> of her Glory, where there ſhall be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſame ſound, and therefore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, all ſweetly together ſinging Hallelujahs to their King. That which ſpoileth the beauty of our Service now, is want of Order, as the moſt exact piece of Beauty may be ill drawn, or the beſt Diſh of meat ſpoil'd with ill cooking. Thoſe Factions and Diviſions which are amongſt us, the ſloven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and naſty carriage of many, that come to our Aſſemblies; and of them alſo, which wait upon the Altar, repreſent Religion deformed, made up of diſproportion; ſo that St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Infidel (if he ſhould come amongſt us) cannot ſay <hi>the Lord is with us of a truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> True Religion is moſt rational, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the Philoſophy of Man's Nature, and the Ends of Diſcourſe. I know ſome Myſteries of our Religion are <hi>ſupra rationem,</hi> [that a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin ſhould bring forth a Son, that the ſame ſhould be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that the dead ſhould riſe again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] but none of theſe are <hi>contra ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi> If you take Religion in a large ſenſe, as ſhe comprehendeth all Virtues, nothing can be more reaſonable than her demands, To fear God, to love our neighbour, to be humble and meek, to honour our parents, to pray for our enemies; What can be more reaſonable? God has now
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104596:12"/>
taken away the rigor and ſeverity of the Law, and given us a yoke to bear, which is more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and the burthen more light. And if I come nearer the Text, you'l find it to be the pureſt reaſon, that God ſhould have the fatteſt of the flock for his portion; the moſt ingenuous and holy obſervance in his Worſhip; the moſt exact order and decency in our approaches to him, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. Now if Religion be thus rational in all her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, it muſt alſo be of a knitting and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting quality, Reaſon being the <hi>ſubſtratum</hi> of all Societies, of all Converſe between man and man. And if we add to this the ſweetneſs of her Nature, exactly anſwering the Converſation of our Bleſſed Saviour, when upon Earth, his Love, Affability, Candor, Humility; nothing certainly can better attract, and draw the Souls of reaſonable men, than Religion. The Profeſſors of it, I confeſs, are ſometimes moroſe and cyni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, not at all inviting in their behaviour; but the fault of them cannot be imputed to our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which (though it does correct,) yet does it not utterly remove the frowardneſs of our Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is delicate and ſpiritual; ſo atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate, that it can penetrate the Soul, raviſh the Thoughts, and command the Conſcience with a holy and ſweet Violence. Good and bad Angels, as they are Spirits, have a power to ſuggeſt good, or bad thoughts: Of this refined ſubſtance
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104596:13"/>
is true Religion, and the Character given of the Word of God, by the Author to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> Chap. 4.12. <hi>That it is quick and powerful, ſharper than any two-edged ſword, piercing even to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding aſunder of ſoul and ſpirit, joynts and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> may very properly repreſent the power which ſhe has upon the ſouls of men; all which are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, laid open and naked before her. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> had eſtabliſhed Order in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> he propheſieth of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting and convincing power that it would have upon the Conſcience, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24. <hi>He is convinced of all; he is judged of all: and thus are the ſecrets of his heart made manifeſt,</hi> &amp;c. At leaſt it has a convincing power; and he that is the moſt debauched upon the face of the earth, is forced to ſhut his eyes, as not able to behold the luſtre and beauty of true Religion.</p>
            <p>Thus have we taken a ſhort view of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Religion; it will now be time to review it in the ſpecial influence it has upon the perſons mentioned in the Text, <hi>God, the King, and the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then, Kings are God's Repreſentatives upon Earth, they bear his Image in a peculiar manner. The worſt and moſt wicked of them declare his ſeverity, in the puniſhments, which they inflict upon offenders with a liberal hand; their Crowns and Scepters ſhow the abſolute
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104596:13"/>
Dominion and Rule which he exerciſeth over all; the Thrones which they ſit upon; his Glory and Majeſty; their vaſt attendance, Officers and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitors ſignifie an innumerable company of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, which as winged Meſſingers, attend the firſt notice of his Will: But, alas! this repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God is but imperfect; we ſee indeed part of his Glory, but no part of his Beauty; rather his back parts, than his face: Men care not much to ſee <hi>Jehovah</hi> cloathed in the Robes of his ſtrength and power, in the Altitudes of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and Greatneſs; the ſight of him, in this manner ſeems terrible, like his appearance upon <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> when he gave forth his Law in lightning and thunder: But the beauties of God's face, which render him moſt acceptable to the ſons and daughters of <hi>Adam,</hi> are conveyed to us only by a Religious Prince, where Juſtice and Mercy, Greatneſs and Goodneſs, Glory and Grace, are ſo ſweetly commixed and attempered, that both Original and Copy, Subſtance and Shadow, God and the King are honoured and adored by all. Such a Prince as this, St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> calls <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matam Dei imaginem,</hi> the Picture of God drawn out to the life; and though there were no other reaſon, yet upon this account he muſt be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctiſſimus Deo:</hi> For as it is but juſt and equal that God ſhould love himſelf firſt and beſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there can be no object ſo perfect as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; ſo is it but rational to believe, that next to himſelf, he will love thoſe beſt who come neareſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104596:14"/>
his Image, and repreſent him moſt amiable to the World: Nor is it improbable, that this is one choice reaſon why <hi>David</hi> is called a <hi>Man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God's own heart, viz.</hi> becauſe he did not only as a Prophet, declare the Glory and Excellency of the divine Majeſty, but as a King in his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and Holy Converſation publiſh the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Princes are Sacred Perſons, <hi>uncti Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini,</hi> the Lord's anointed; the worſt, as well as the beſt; as well <hi>Nero,</hi> as <hi>David;</hi> as well <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Nebat,</hi> who made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin, as <hi>Solomon; for there is no power,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>but of God;</hi> he is the Fountain and Original of all: But Religious Kings are <hi>Sacro-ſancti,</hi> as they have devoted themſelves to the Honour of their great Lord and Maſter. This maketh the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ſo careful and tender of their welfare, that not the weight of a finger muſt lye upon them without a curſe, ſaying, <hi>Touch not mine anointed.</hi> And it ſeems, by the cuſtom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, to be a principle in Nature; for it was uſual with them to make Virtuous and Renowned Princes, the companions of the Gods, <hi>Referre eos in numerum Deorum,</hi> to reckon them amongſt the Gods.</p>
            <q>Diviſum imperium cum Jove Caeſar habet.</q>
            <p>The <hi>Greeks,</hi> and eſpecially their Poets had as Phantaſtical opinions of their Hero's and Demons, they phancied their departure out of this world
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104596:14"/>
to be a Tranſlation only, for preſently you find them amongſt the Gods of near relation to <hi>Jupiter, Jove Satus, &amp; Jove Ortus; Homer</hi> abounds in ſuch inſtances. The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> though ſhe has no great reſpect for Emperors and Kings; yet the homage which old <hi>Rome</hi> paid to their Princes, ſhe offers to her Saints; whom though ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth to Deifie, yet at leaſt ſhe Divifies, and too liberally gives them Divine Worſhip. By all theſe inſtances you may ſee, as in a glaſs, how wonderfully Religion does exalt a perſon, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially a Prince, in the love of the Almighty, placing him under the direct beams of his Power and Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Religious Princes are <hi>ex naturâ Dei,</hi> partakers of the divine Nature, <hi>I ſaid ye are Gods.</hi> I confeſs all Princes are ſo <hi>virtute officii;</hi> but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Princes <hi>ex naturâ rei,</hi> as they are in an extraordinary manner ſpirited and furniſhed by God for Government; their Souls uſually are larger by far, than other mens; their hearts are deeper. <hi>Saul,</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is ſent to the School of the Prophets, and there taught to prophecy, before he wears the Crown, or ſways the Scepter: His Succeſſor <hi>David</hi> was alſo a Prophet, indued with a noble and divine Spirit. The Wiſe man tells us, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.3. <hi>That the hearts of Kings are unſearchable, not to be fathom'd. Moſes</hi> was poſſeſs'd of this glorious Spirit, it had been otherwiſe impoſſible to have govern'd that ſtubborn and unruly people, which at laſt tired
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104596:15"/>
our his patience; and it is worthy obſervation, when God was pleaſed to eaſe him of ſome part of the burthen, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.17. he ſpake thus to him: <hi>I will come down, and talk with thee, and will take off the Spirit which is upon thee, and will put it upon them, and they ſhall be as the burthen of the people with thee.</hi> In all theſe reſpects, Religious and Holy Princes, as <hi>Menander</hi> obſerves, are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the very Images of God; and therefore they muſt be nigh unto him, and he unto them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As true Religion does unite God and the King, ſo alſo the King and the People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> As it maketh the heart of a Prince truly noble and generous; for there is no School that can ſo excellently improve a Prince, as true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; no Precepts ſo refined, to furniſh him with Wiſdom for all parts of Government; no policy ſo true and ſucceſsful; no learning does ſo exactly and preciſely declare the duties of the one to the other as the Word of God; ſo that what Prince ſoever he be, that takes pleaſure to govern ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thoſe Rules, muſt needs be magnified in the eyes of his Subjects: Theſe are the men that beſt deſerve the names of <hi>Patres Patriae,</hi> to be reverenced, honoured, and eſteemed of all. What a tender regard had the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for <hi>David;</hi> by no means muſt he endanger his Perſon in the battel, for in their eye he was more worth than ten thouſand of them. Good <hi>Joſiah</hi> did better deſerve the name of <hi>Delicium humani
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104596:15"/>
generis,</hi> than <hi>Caeſar:</hi> obſerve how the people la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment him, by the lips and eyes of the weeping Prophet, <hi>Lament.</hi> 4.20. <hi>The breath of our noſtrils, the anointed of the Lord was token in their nets: of whom we ſaid, Under his ſhadow we ſhall be preſerved alive among the heathen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is imprinted upon the Nature of man, a ſpecial reverence for Holineſs and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which you may eaſily perceive in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, who (tho they ſeldom underſtand what true Religion is) yet how do they hug and embrace the very rumour and report of it? Let Religion beat up a drum, and you cannot allay the heat of their ſpirits; they muſt follow the noiſe of it. This makes Satan, in our days, put on the appearance of an Angel of light; and every jugling Enthuſiaſt will pretend Sanctity and Religion, when he deſigneth to obtrude his own blaſphemies upon the World. How many miſerable Souls are trepan'd into the thraldom of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church by a Religious bluſh, which ſits upon the face of her Worſhip? It was no hard matter for the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> to ſwallow down whole houſes under the pretence of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Politicks, gives this advice to <hi>Traj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the Emperor, <hi>Venerare Deos, &amp; per pietatem in co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m honorem opibus tuis utare, magno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere enim multitudo affici ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, dum pietatem coram conſpiciunt; quos maximi ducunt.</hi> This got <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> ſuch an. excellent name, <hi>Quod plurima fana, lucoſque Deorum dedicavit.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:104596:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The great deſign of: Chriſtian Religion, eſpecially the publick and ſolemn Worſhip of God, is to render men alike one to another, of one heart, mind, way, and life: Our prayers are the ſame, that all of us, as one man, may conſent to ſay <hi>Amen.</hi> Our Diſcourſes either are, or ſhould be the ſame, differing in phraſe and manner of utterance; yet bearing proportion <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to the wholeſome form of ſound words. We are initiated after the ſame manner by Baptiſm into one and the ſame Church, at the Euchariſt fed at the ſame table with the ſame bread, refreſhed with the ſame wine, by all incorporated, that being one body, all the members may have a mutual reſpect, and care one of another. St. <hi>Paul</hi> upon this conſideration magnifieth the Chriſtian Religion, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.3. as <hi>keeping the unity of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> and commends it in the next words, for the power that it carrieth to ſecure the common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of love, which he calleth the <hi>bond of peace;</hi> the reaſonableneſs of which he evinceth, <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>There is one body, as there is one ſpirit; as likewiſe ye are called into one hope of your calling: One Lord, one faith, one baptiſme, one God, and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in all things.</hi> The whole body of Religion is comprized in this word <hi>Love;</hi> and we may judge of the ſincere profeſſors of it, by their conformity to it. Thus have I done with the ſecond particular, the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting nature of true Religion.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:104596:16"/>
            <p>The third and laſt Enquiry is, What priviledge the Text alloweth to a Nation, or People, whilſt they are zealous and devout in Religious Worſhip, thus expreſſed: <hi>Then ſhall ye, and the King which reigneth over you, continue to follow the Lord.</hi> In the Original there is nothing at all found for <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing;</hi> all that is there expreſſed, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which Tranſlators have rendered as you read; the Septuagint does not much differ, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>walking behind,</hi> or <hi>after the Lord;</hi> the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which muſt be, that as God, when they had no King, was their Captain, leading forth their Armies, and giving them ſucceſs and victory, (for this was the great reaſon they urged for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of Government, that they might have a King to go out before them, and ſo fight their battels); ſo alſo upon due obſervation of Religious Worſhip, by him appointed, he would ſtill be their General, and under his Banner they ſhould ſight victoriouſly over their Adverſaries. Now that this bleſſing is not meerly temporary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing only to that people, but entailed upon Piety and Religion to all generations, is evident from the conſtant care, and tender reſpect he hath continued to his Church, to this day; for accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his promiſe, that the <hi>gates of Hell ſhall never prevail againſt it:</hi> ſo it is, and ſo it ſhall be, ſo long as the world endureth.</p>
            <p>And leſt it ſhould be objected, that Promiſes of this nature are peculiar to the Church Univerſal, and have no reference to particular Churches, or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104596:17"/>
Nations, (although true Religion be therein pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and incouraged); let it be remembered, that what belongs to the whole, belongs alſo to the part; and though many particular Churches formerly renowned, are now utterly extinct, as the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and many more; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their ruine, they had a charge of notorious crimes drawn up againſt them, and notice of thoſe exterminating Judgments, which (without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) would follow. God does very rarely, if ever, deal with Churches, or Societies of men, as with Individuals: theſe he oftentimes leaveth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der diſmal and ſore afflictions; not ſo much for the demerit of their Sins, as the probation of their Graces. This was the caſe of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom,</hi> of holy <hi>Job,</hi> who had this excellent cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter from God, at the very inſtant, when he ſealed a Commiſſion to Satan to afflict him, that he was an upright and perfect man. But who can tell of a Righteous Nation, which hath kept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violate the Judgments and Statutes of Heaven, that was ever forſaken by God? If you pleaſe to look home, you will find the never failing Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of the Almighty to watch over this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for good; ſo long as we kept our Garments clean; ſo long as Religion flouriſhed, and the Corruptions thereof were diſcountenanced. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity attended the long Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> although the Enemies of our Church were more numerous then, and as buſie and active as they are now. The peaceable bringing in of King
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104596:17"/>
               <hi>James,</hi> almoſt to a Miracle, was a demonſtration of the kindneſs which God had for a people una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous, (for then neither Popery nor Phanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm were tolerated.) All the time he reigned both Church and State, were in a proſperous condition; but as ſoon as ever extravagant ſpirits began to break the unity of the ſpirit by Faction, then did God righteouſly begin to break the bond of peace. And it is farther obſervable, that when the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>England</hi> waxed wanton in their Religion, then alſo did they become immoral, looſe, and debauched in their lives; for Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſm, Factions in the Church, and Adulteries, Fornication, Drunkenneſs, Prophaneneſs in the State, are but <hi>gemini fratres,</hi> which come into the world at one and the ſame time. If we look for a reaſon why men of all ſorts, rich and poor, the Lord and the Beggar are ſo daring and confident in all kind of licentiouſneſs, as if there were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Heaven nor Hell, God, or Devil, you need not go far, Religion hath not been encouraged, which was always, and ever will be (may ſhe be protected) a curb to all Impiety.</p>
            <p>If any man therefore ſhall ask why the promiſe of the Text is not made good to <hi>England,</hi> why we are in a trembling, dangerous condition? The Anſwer is near; Proteſtants have declined in their Zeal; abated in their love to Religion: theſe burned gloriouſly a conſiderable time after the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, but now their heat and light are both impaired. Some are turned <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and ſo hate
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104596:18"/>
Religion; others are turned <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and ſo corrupt it; a multitude are become froward <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> and at this day are tearing and renting it into pieces.</p>
            <p>The proud Atheiſt ſcorns to be control'd; his tongue is his own, and he will be Lord of it. Tuſh, doth the Lord ſee? and is there any knowledge in the moſt high? <hi>He hath ſaid in his heart, There is no God:</hi> And this abominable Principle openeth a ſluce for a whole flood and deluge of all Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Eſſe aliquos manes, &amp; ſubterranea regna,</l>
               <l>Et Contum, &amp; Stigio ranas in gurgite nigras</l>
               <l>Nec pueri credunt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>They will not believe any thing of this nature, unleſs ſometimes God doth extort it. St. <hi>Paul</hi> met with this herd of men, rather beaſts, that were laughing at the reſurrection of the dead, as a meer cheat impoſed upon the world to keep it quiet, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. And the abominable concluſion which they draw from theſe horrid Premiſes, you may there read, <hi>Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we ſhall dye; i. e.</hi> after death we ſhall neither taſte nor ſmell, but be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilated; and therefore let us have as great a ſhare of pleaſure, as we can, before it cometh. Can it be well with the Nation, whilſt this Vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous brood are ſuffered to rant and hector in the World, venture into Gentlemens company, diffuſe their poyſon, take liberty to baffle young and old, to make as many Proſelytes to Hell as they can?
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104596:18"/>
Theſe men that deſerve the worſt of Deaths for their blaſphemy, at leaſt to have their tongues cut out, are the Gallants of the time, and no man muſt be ſo ſaucy as to controle them. Can there be peace, whilſt theſe go unpuniſhed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Hereticks corrupt our Religion: for this is the next piece of Satan's damnable policy; if he cannot club down true Religion, and force it out of the world, he will make it as uſeleſs, as may be, in the world, by ſpoiling the ſimplicity, and adulterating the purity of it: His inſtruments are always prepared to ſerve this curſed turn, men that are reſerved, cloſe, carrying the faireſt ſhow of Religion, that with more facility they may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found it. <hi>Neſtorius</hi> will by no means deny the Bleſſed Virgin to be the Mother of Chriſt, but ſhe muſt not be the Mother of God, ſubtilly deſigning thereby to ſpoil the glorious office of a Mediator. We have too many amongſt us at this day, who have ſwallowed down the poyſon of this curſed Doctrine, granting that Chriſt dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> without the gate; but they will not own him to be a Saviour of the World: He was indeed a good man, but not <hi>ab aterno;</hi> there was a time when he was neither God, nor Man. I ſhould be too tedious in enumerating many inſtances of this nature, there being (I believe) no Article of our Creed, which at this day is not depraved: We are not without <hi>Arians, Socinians, Munſterians,</hi> &amp;c. who tho they lye ſnug and cloſe, not appearing like the broad fac'd <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> yet are they as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104596:19"/>
to Church and State, and as great diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the peace of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as the former.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, The angry Schiſmatick, who tho he profeſſeth the ſame Faith and Doctrine with our Church, yet does he ſcorn that any ſhould conduct his Zeal in the Worſhip of God: Whereas a truly pious, and humble Soul, whether he be of the Clergy, or Laity, entertaineth low thoughts of himſelf, and is willing to be guided in thoſe things that concern Diſcipline; the other is proud, ſelf-conceited, and thinks that he is more fit to govern, than to be governed. I confeſs Charity commands me to believe, that ſome Diſſenters have better hearts, but theſe may eaſily be differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced from the reſt, by their meekneſs, patience, readineſs to be informed: But when men have brazen brows, Iron necks, I cannot conceive how they ſhould have tender conſciences; and let them pretend to what they pleaſe, yet till I ſee them faſhioned to the ſweetneſs of the Goſpel of Chriſt, I cannot perſwade my ſelf, that they aim at the Glory of God, or the Exaltation of true Religion.</p>
            <p>But are there none elſe, none amongſt our ſelves, who deprive us of the bleſſed influence of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe? I fear we cannot excuſe our ſelves. Our want of devotion, our irreverence and hypocriſie in the preſence of Almighty God will bear witneſs againſt us. We rather bring our pomp and gallantry with us into the publick Aſſemblies, than our conſciences; our eyes, than our ears; our faces, than our faith; our luſts than our graces; we look not upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104596:19"/>
as our buſineſs, but rather our diverſion; not the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of our ſouls, but the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of our fancies. When I conſider how devout Heathens have been at the Worſhip of their Idols; with what fear and reverence they approach their Deities; what ſtudy to make them propitious; how ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, not daring to ſtrike the firſt blow, nor begin a battel, till they have killed their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and found out the <hi>fauſtum omen.</hi> When I read how cogent <hi>Pliny</hi> is in his Panegyrick to his <hi>Mecaenas, nihil benè, riteque auſpicandum, ſine Deorum immortalium natu, &amp; conſilio;</hi> how penitent and ſorrowful they have been, when ſenſible of any neglect in Religion.</p>
            <p>It may cauſe Chriſtians to bluſh at the indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency and looſeneſs of their behaviour before the All-ſeeing God. When I ſee our Congregations full of thoſe men and women, which St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> complaineth of in his days, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, dull, ſottiſh, ſleepy ſouls, ſnoring, yawning, I may add whiſpering, laughing, intent upon, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs than Religion. Laſtly, When I conſider the immoralities of all, from the higheſt to the loweſt, of Prieſt and People, rich and poor, the common and bloody Oaths, the National drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, adulteries, fornication, murders, too common and rife amongſt us; there cannot, methinks, be any room left for this Queſtion, Why is it thus with <hi>England,</hi> ſince we profeſs true Religion? but rather why are we not as <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> as <hi>Adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h</hi> and <hi>Zeboiim,</hi> ſince our abominations are
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104596:20"/>
as weighty and numerous as theirs were? I have no more to add to this firſt Propoſition, but to leave theſe few words to your conſideration; That as it was neglect of Religion, which did firſt open a wide and effectual door, through which crouded in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us all Impieties, and both together have cauſed the Heavens to look ſable and black over us; ſo muſt Religion be exalted to her former ſimplicity and obſervance, before we can expect the face of our God to ſhine upon us; which will lead me to this ſhort word of Application.</p>
            <p>You ſee, Right Honourable, both our wounds, and the cure of them, the only reſtorative of our conſumptive, both Church and State; uſe, I beſeech you, with all diligence and ſpeed this healing plaiſter; pour of this bleſſed Oyl into our wounds; let us not bleed to death in the lap of our abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, although it be an eaſie death; Oh! let not an Icy ſlumber ſeal up our eyes to everlaſting darkneſs. We are brought low, very low, if the floods of Irreligion and Impiety be not ſtopped, our deſtruction cannot be far. Stir up your ſelves therefore to a due conſideration of our danger; be ſtrong and couragious, you that have power to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs all Prophaneneſs; let not the wild beaſts of the Forreſt, wicked and debauched perſons, trample under their prophane feet, the Royal and Holy Law; it's below a Chriſtian to be a meer man, when the intereſts of God and Religion lye at the ſtake. Indeavour, I beſeech you, to eſtabliſh Unity, as well as Purity in Religion. Why ſhould men, without
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104596:20"/>
controle, take liberty againſt Law, not only to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from our publick Aſſemblies, but ſet up Altar againſt Altar? Reaſonable men would ſoon be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to frequent our Congregations, were it not for them who are heady, high-minded, and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, men that love to Proſelyte ſilly ſouls, that they may ſerve to maintain their own Factions, whilſt they exerciſe a ſordid Juriſdiction over their Conſciences. I confeſs it's a vanity to go about to knock down mens reaſon, or to capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate their minds by force; let them abound in their own ſenſe, pleaſe their own fancies in their retirements; but in publick worſhip, where we are all alike intereſſed, there, I beſeech you, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend earneſtly for a bleſſed agreement. Every river and rivulet will have its private murmurs, according to thoſe Eddies and turns which oppoſe their waters; but the Ocean, into which they all empty themſelves, hath but one ſound; it were deſirable that every Chriſtian were a good Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy, able to govern himſelf and family accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Laws of God and his Church; but who looks into corners, or digs a hole through his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Wall, to pry into his Family-devotions? But no leſs can be expected, then that upon ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn days of Worſhip they ſhould be ready to joyn with us, in ſetting forth the praiſes of our gracious God, and preſenting our Petitions at the Throne of his Mercy. This is the counſel of the Text; which if we will entertain, we may ſtill continue to follow the Lord; if not, I muſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104596:21"/>
leave to your conſideration the laſt Verſe of the Text, <hi>The hand of the Lord ſhall be againſt you, as it was againſt your Fathers.</hi> Which God of his infinite Mercy divert, for the ſake of our deareſt Lord: To whom with thee, O Father, and the Holy Spirit, be all Glory and Praiſe for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:104596:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
